Finding Aid for Theodore Hawley Tapping papers, 1909-1916 and 1937-1961
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Theodore Hawley Tapping papers 1909-1916 and 1937-1961
Tapping, Theodore Hawley, 1889-1969.
2.3 linear feet and 1 oversize volume.
86102 Aa 2
Secretary of University of Michigan Alumni Association; correspondence, scrapbooks, and photographs.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The bulk of the collection was donated by Tapping (donor 1464 ) in 1951 and 1959-1960. Some materials were donated by the University of Michigan Alumni Association (donor 1617 ).
No further additions to the papers are expected.
The collection is open to research.
T. Hawley Tapping was born on Aug. 13, 1889, in Peoria, IL. He attended the University of Michigan literary college from 1907 to 1909. Tapping then received his Bachelor of Arts degree from the State University of Iowa in 1911.
Tapping began his career as newspaper editor for two years for several newspapers, including the Peoria Transcript of Peoria, IL. He then returned to the University of Michigan to receive his law degree in 1916. During World War I, Tapping served with the 343rd U.S. Infantry of the American Expeditionary Force in France for two years, rising to the rank of captain.
T. Hawley Tapping was a member of the Acacia fraternity and was national editor for that social fraternity in 1920-28. In addition, Tapping in 1921 became state editor of the Grand Rapids Press. In 1922-23, he was appointed Ann Arbor correspondent for the Booth Newspapers of Michigan. And in 1923, he became Field Secretary for the U-M Alumni Association, later General Secretary and editor-in-chief of the Michigan Alumnus. He retired in 1958.
Following his retirement, Tapping was appointed to the United Board of New York as a consultant to Stillman University in the Philippines, a Presbyterian Church supported institution. In 1962 he was named by the Washtenaw County Chapter of the American Red Cross as a consultant for its fund-raising drive to build the chapter's present headquarters on Packard Rd.
Tapping died on February 17, 1969.
The T. Hawley Tapping collection includes material documenting his student days at the University of Michigan and University of Iowa, the Acacia fraterity and his work as consultant to Silliman University in the Philippine Islands and service to the University of Michigan Alumni Association. The papers are arranged into three series: Correspondence; Scrapbooks; and Photographs.
Subjects:
Acacia Fraternity.; Angell, James Burrill, 1829-1916.; Philippines--History--1946-1986.; Silliman University.; University of Iowa.; University of Michigan--Alumni and alumnae.; University of Michigan. Alumni Association.; University of Michigan--Students--Social life and customs--1901-1910.; University of Michigan--Students--Social life and customs--1911-1920.; World War, 1939-1945.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Acacia Fraternity.; Archons (University of Michigan); Farming.; Football.; Griffins (University of Michigan); Tapping, Theodore Hawley, 1889-1969.; University of Iowa.; University of Michigan--Football.; University of Michigan. Junior Hop.; University of Michigan--Student housing.; University of Michigan--Students--1911-1920.; Hazing--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; University of Michigan--Students--Conduct of life.; Women college students--Michigan--Ann Arbor.
Contributors:
Murphy, George, 1897-1961.; Murphy, Irene Ellis, 1900-; Ruthven, Alexander Grant, 1882-1971.
Genre Terms:
Calling cards.; Photographs.; Scrapbooks.
- Correspondence
  The Correspondence concerns the gift of land to the University of Michigan by the Von Platen-Fox Company. There are also letters from servicemen during World War II, including Milton M. Berger, army physician, who comments on the surrender of a group of Japanese on Okinawa at the end of World War II. The correspondence also relates to Tapping's activities in the Philippine Islands as consultant to Silliman University in its public relations program. Also found in the correspondence are letters from various University alumni containing reminiscences of administration of James B. Angell, and founding of the Acacia Fraternity. Other correspondents include George Murphy, Irene Murphy, and Alexander Ruthven.
  - 1937 (Von Platen-Fox Company) (Box 1)
  - 1939-1946 (Box 1)
  - 1956-September 1961, 40 folders (Box 1)
- Scrapbooks (College)
  The Scrapbooks contain programs, pictures, calling cards, and miscellanea, ca. 1908-1915, from Iowa University and University of Michigan.
  - 1909-1910 (Box 2)
    (includes photos of buildings, student activites, and student rooms at University of Iowa)
  - 1910-1911 (Box 2)
    (includes photos of student activities at University of Iowa)
  - 1911-1913 (Box 2)
  - 1913-1914 (Box 2)
  - 1914-1915 (Volume 1)
    (includes photos of Archons and Griffins initiations)
  - 1914-1916 (Box 2)
  - Loose material from scrapbooks, chiefly photos, 5 folders (Box 3)
- Photographs
  The Photographs relate to Tapping's student life at the University of Michigan and University of Iowa, including photos of student rooms, football games, the 1916 Junior Hop, Acacia fraternity, and initiations of the Archons and Griffins.
  - Family and friends (Box 3)
  - Junior Hop, 1916 (Box 3)
  - Portraits (Box 3)
  - Sports (Box 3)
  - University of Michigan buildings and students (Box 3)